PRASHANT K. JHA

6.328 POB The University of Texas at Austin · 225-249-9456 pjha.sci@gmail.com · prashjha.github.io · twitter/Prashant_j160

My research interests include computational modeling, computational oncology, continuum and fracture mechanics, and numerical analysis. I am interested in application of mathematical models and high-performance computational resources to key and present-day relevant problems.

EXPERIENCE

2020-09-16 - PRESENT

POSTDOCTORAL SCHOLAR, THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN

Department: Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences

Work description: Perform research, present work in seminar and conference, collaborate and exchange ideas, write proposals.

2019-08-01 - 2020-09-15

POSTDOCTORAL SCHOLAR, THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN

Department: Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences

Adviser: Dr. J. Tinsley Oden

Work description: Perform research, present work in seminar and conference, collaborate and

exchange ideas, write proposals.

2016-10-01 - 2019-07-31

POSTDOCTORAL SCHOLAR, LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY

Department: Department of Mathematics

Adviser: Dr. Robert Lipton

Work description: Perform research, present work in seminar and conference, collaborate and

exchange ideas, write proposals.

EDUCATION

2012-08-01 - 2016-09-07

PhD, CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY

Department: Civil and Environmental Engineering

Adviser: Dr. Kaushik Dayal

Project: Coarse graining of electric field interactions with materials

2010-08-01 - 2012-06-30

ME, INDIAN INSTITUTE OF SCIENCE, BANGALORE

Department: Mechanical Engineering

Adviser: Dr. C. S. Jog

Project: A monolithic strategy for fluid-structure interaction in compressible flow

2006-08-01 - 2010-06-30

BE, NEW GOVERNMENT ENGINEERING COLLEGE, RAIPUR

Department: Mechanical Engineering

MAJOR PROJECTS

2020-09-01 - PRESENT

A MECHANISTIC TUMOR GROWTH MODEL FOR HP MRI

- HP MRI techniques show tremendous potential for identification of tumor legions in a
 patient. Currently, ODE-based compartmental models are utilized to recover the signal
 from the imaging data. In this project, we consider a 1D-3D PDE-based model which
 explicitly accounts for heterogeneous flow in the tissue due to vasculature.
- This is supported by a pilot project grant under the joint initiative of Oden institute-MD Anderson-TACC.
- In collaboration with Dr. J. T. Oden (UT Austin) and Dr. D. Fuentes (MD Anderson Cancer Center)

2020-01-01 - PRESENT

APPLICATION OF PHYSICS-INFORMED NEURAL NETWORK TO TUMOR GROWTH

- Our objective in this project is to find the scenarios where Physics-informed neural networks (PINNs) can be applied to study and better understanding of the tumor growth in the tissue.
- In collaboration with Dr. J. T. Oden (UT Austin)

2019-08-01 - PRESENT

DEVELOPMENT OF MODELS OF TUMOR GROWTH

- In this project, we aim to develop a realistic simulator of growth/decline of tumor in cancerous tissue. This has two major applications: 1. Testing various treatment hypothesis, and 2. Recovery of information from the imaging data. Towards this, we have proposed a 3D-1D model that couples the flow of blood and substances in the vessels to the constituents in the tissue.
- In collaboration with Dr. J. T. Oden (UT Austin) and researchers at Technical University of Munich

2016-10-01 - PRESENT

NUMERICAL ANALYSIS AND APPLICATION OF PERIDYNAMICS MODELS

- Peridynamics is a reformulation of classical continuum mechanics that has shown good success in describing the fracture in solids in a unified way. Aims of the project include numerical analysis of peridynamic models, application of the models, and study of the hidden properties of peridynamics and its relationship with the classical theory of fracture (LEFM).
- In collaboration with Dr. Robert Lipton and Dr. Patrick Diehl at Louisiana State University

2019-08-01 - PRESENT

DEVELOPMENT OF MASSIVELY PARALLEL LIBRARY FOR PERIDYNAMICS

• Together with Dr. P. Diehl at LSU, we are working on development of efficient and massively parallel library for peridynamics simulations.

 Towards this goal, we recently concluded a 3-4 months long Google Summer of Code 2020 event in which we introduced and mentored a project entitled "Domain decomposition, load balancing, and massively parallel solvers for the class of nonlocal models".

REFEREED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

*Under review, †book chapter

[2020-6]	Kinetic relations and local energy balance for LEFM from a nonlocal peridynamic model Prashant K Jha and Robert Lipton International Journal of Fracture, 5 September 2020, Link
[2020-5]	Bayesian-based predictions of COVID-19 evolution in Texas using multispecies mixture-theoretic continuum models Prashant K Jha, Lianghao Cao, and J. Tinsley Oden Computational Mechanics, 31 July 2020, Link
[2020-4]*	Plane elastodynamic solutions for running cracks as the limit of double well nonlocal dynamics Robert Lipton and Prashant K Jha arXiv:2001.00313 (under review July 2020), Link
[2020-3]	Finite element convergence for state-based peridynamic fracture models Prashant K Jha and Robert Lipton Communications on Applied Mathematics and Computation, March 2020, 2, 93-128, Link
[2020-2]*	Analysis of a new multispecies tumor growth model coupling 3D phase-fields with a 1D vascular network Marvin Fritz, Prashant K Jha, Tobias Köppl, J Tinsley Oden, Barbara Wohlmuth arXiv:2006.10477 (under review June 2020), Link
[2020-1]	Finite element approximation of nonlocal dynamic fracture models Prashant K Jha and Robert Lipton Discrete & Continuous Dynamical Systems - B, June 2020, 22, Link
[2019-2]	Numerical convergence of finite difference approximations for state based peridynamic fracture models Prashant K Jha and Robert Lipton Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineering, 21 March 2019, 351, 184-225, Link
[2019-1]	Complex fracture nucleation and evolution with nonlocal elastodynamics Robert Lipton, Richard B Lehoucq, and Prashant K Jha Journal of Peridynamics and Nonlocal Modeling, 25 April 2019, 1, 122-130, Link

[2018-8]†	Well-Posed Nonlinear Nonlocal Fracture Models Associated with Double-Well Potentials Prashant K Jha and Robert Lipton In: Voyiadjis G. (eds) Handbook of Nonlocal Continuum Mechanics for Materials and Structures, 26 April 2018, 1-40, Link
[2018-7]†	Finite difference and finite element in nonlocal fracture modeling: A-priori convergence rates Prashant K Jha and Robert Lipton In: Voyiadjis G. (eds) Handbook of Nonlocal Continuum Mechanics for Materials and Structures, 18 May 2018, 1-38, Link
[2018-6]†	Dynamic brittle fracture from non-local double well potentials: A state-based model Robert Lipton, Eyad Said, and Prashant K. Jha In: Voyiadjis G. (eds) Handbook of Nonlocal Continuum Mechanics for Materials and Structures, 12 March 2018, 1-27, Link
[2018-5]†	Dynamic damage propagation with memory: A state-based model Robert Lipton, Eyad Said, and Prashant K. Jha In: Voyiadjis G. (eds) Handbook of Nonlocal Continuum Mechanics for Materials and Structures, 16 March 2018, 1-29, Link
[2018-4]	Numerical convergence of nonlinear nonlocal continuum models to local elastodynamics Prashant K Jha and Robert Lipton International Journal for Numerical Methods in Engineering, 24 May 2018, 114(13), 1389-1410, Link
[2018-3]	Numerical analysis of nonlocal fracture models in Hölder space Prashant K Jha and Robert Lipton SIAM Journal on Numerical Analysis, 10 April 2018, 56(2), 906-941, Link
[2018-2]*	Implementation of Peridynamics utilizing HPXthe C++ standard library for parallelism and concurrency Patrick Diehl, Prashant K Jha, Hartmut Kaiser, Robert Lipton, Martin Levesque arXiv:1806.06917 (Under review), Link
[2018-1]	Free damage propagation with memory Robert Lipton, Eyad Said, and Prashant K. Jha Journal of Elasticity, 14 March 2018, 133(2), 129-153, <u>Link</u>

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITY

2020-10-09, SEMINAR, CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY, PITTSBURGH Department: Civil and Environmental Engineering

Title: A mechanistic tumor growth model for HP MRI

2020-09-16, SEMINAR, THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN, AUSTIN Department: Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences

Title: A mechanistic tumor growth model for HP MRI

2019-08-20, SEMINAR, THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN, AUSTIN

Department: Oden Institute for Computational Engineering and Sciences Title: Numerical fracture experiments using nonlinear nonlocal models

2019-08-20, CONFERENCE, US NATIONAL CONGRESS ON COMPUTATIONAL MECHANICS 15, AUSTIN

Title: Numerical fracture experiments using nonlinear nonlocal models

2019-07-17, CONFERENCE, ICIAM 2019, VALENCIA

Title: Convergence results for finite element and finite difference approximation of nonlocal fracture

2019-04-12, SEMINAR, INDIAN INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY, DELHI

Department: Mechanical Engineering

Title: Modelling fracture in solids using nonlocal interaction: A brief overview of Peridynamics

2018-10-06, CONFERENCE, SIAM TX LA MEETING 2018, BATON ROUGE

Title: Convergence results for finite element and finite difference approximation of nonlocal fracture models

2018-07-25, CONFERENCE, WORLD CONGRESS ON COMPUTATIONAL MECHANICS 13, NEWYORK

Title: Free damage propagation with memory

2018-05-01, SEMINAR, INDIAN INSTITUTE OF SCIENCE, BANGALORE

Department: Department of Mathematics

Title: Well-posedness of nonlocal fracture models and apriori error estimates of numerical approximations

2018-03-19, SEMINAR, LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY, BATON ROUGE

Department: Department of Mathematics

Title: Finite element approximation of nonlocal fracture models

2017-07-19, CONFERENCE, US NATIONAL CONGRESS ON COMPUTATIONAL MECHANICS 14,

MONTREAL

Title: Numerical Analysis of Nonlocal Fracture Models

2017-04-04, SEMINAR, UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA TWIN CITIES, MINNEAPOLIS

Department: Institute for Mathematics and its Applications

Title: Numerical Analysis of Nonlocal Fracture Models

2017-04-04, SEMINAR, UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA TWIN CITIES, MINNEAPOLIS

Department: Aerospace Engineering and Mechanics

Title: Coarse Graining of Electric Field Interactions with Materials

2016-08-22, SEMINAR, INDIAN INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY, MADRAS

Department: Mechanical Engineering

Title: Coarse Graining of Electric Field Interactions with Materials

2016-08-19, SEMINAR, INDIAN INSTITUTE OF SCIENCE, BANGALORE

Department: Mechanical Engineering

Title: Coarse Graining of Electric Field Interactions with Materials

PROPOSALS AND GRANTS

2020-09-01 - 2021-08-31

A MECHANISTIC TUMOR GROWTH MODEL FOR HP MRI

Description: Awarded under the joint initiative of Oden Institute-MDACC-TACC

GROUP AFFILIATIONS

USACM SIAM

AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

• GATE Exam: All India rank 31 in GATE-2010

 Best TA award for finite element methods (May 2013)

Dean's fellowship (for 1st year of PhD)

REFERENCES

Dr. J. Tinsley Oden

Email: oden@oden.utexas.edu

Website: https://jtoden.oden.utexas.edu/

Phone: 512-471-3312

POB 6.324

The University of Texas at Austin

Austin, TX 78712

Dr. Robert Lipton

Email: lipton@lsu.edu

Website: https://www.math.lsu.edu/~lipton/

Phone: 225-578-1569

258 Lockett Hall

Louisiana State University Baton Rouge, LA 70803

Dr. Kaushik Dayal

Email: Kaushik.Dayal@cmu.edu

Website: https://sites.google.com/view/kaushik-

dayal-research-group Phone: 412-268-2949 123J Porter Hall

Carnegie Mellon University

Pittsburgh, PA 15213

Dr. Jiuyi Zhu

Email: zhu@math.lsu.edu

Website: https://www.math.lsu.edu/~zhu/

Phone: 225-578-1665

228 Lockett Hall

Louisiana State University

Baton Rouge, LA 70803

Dr. Amit Acharya

Email: acharyaamit@cmu.edu

Website: https://faculty.ce.cmu.edu/acharya/

Phone: 412-268-4566

Dr. Chandrashekhar S. Jog

Email: jogc@iisc.ac.in

Website:

http://www.mecheng.iisc.ac.in/users/jogc

Phone: +91-80-22932957

101 Porter Hall Carnegie Mellon University Pittsburgh, PA 15213

307 Mechanical Engineering Building Department of Mechanical Engineering Indian Institute of Science Bengaluru, India 560012